שבוע טוב *Shavua tov*, good Moed. Today's דף *daf* is פ"ד *Pe
Dalet*, 84, the last דף *daf* of הנשרפים *HaNisrafim*. We pick up
on the bottom of פ"ג עמוד ב' *Pe Gimmel Amud Bet*. We
just went through a whole fun סוגיה *sugya* about קנאים פוגעים בו
kana'im pogim bo *Kna'im Pogim Bo* and פנחס *Pinchas*, and I should
just mention, I happen to see, since we haven't had a chance
to be doing ירושלמי Yerushalmi *Yerushalmi*, but I happened to see that
the ירושלמי Yerushalmi *Yerushalmi* actually about פנחס *Pinchas* says that what פנחס
*Pinchas* did was שלא ברצון חכמים chachamim *she-lo birtzon chachamim*. What he
did was against sort of what the rabbis would have wanted, and
that it actually says that at the time that he did it,
בני ישראל Yisrael *Bnei Yisrael* wanted to put him in חרם *cherem*,
were it not that the divine voice came out and said הנני
נותן לו את בריתי שלום *Hinneni noten lo et briti shalom*. So
just again sort of reinforcing that idea that on the one hand
you have the קנאים פוגעים בו bo *Kna'im Pogim Bo*, but at
the other hand it's very much operating outside of the law, consistent
with the בבלי'ס *Bavli's* idea that זמרי *Zimri* could have turned around
and killed פנחס *Pinchas* as a רודף rodef *rodef*. So I just
thought that ירושלמי Yerushalmi *Yerushalmi* was a nice compliment to that. But
anyway, back to what we're dealing with, yesterday's דף *daf* was really
devoted to a whole list of the things that you're חייב מיתה
chayav misa, בידי שמים bidei shamayim. *chayav misa bidei shamayim*. Seems to
be getting onto it as a digression, but could also be related
to the fact that we're dealing with all of these executions of
the court, we also want a list of things that you're חייב
מיתה chayav misa, בידי שמים *chayav misa bidei shamayim*. And pretty much
all of them, maybe not all, but like the vast majority, are
related to things of either עבודה avoda *avoda* in the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash *Beit HaMikdash* or קדשים *Kodshim* or those types of issues.
Okay, so we pick up with the bottom, two lines from the
bottom on פ"ג עמוד ב' *Pe Gimmel Amud Bet*. אבל ערל אונן
יושב *Aval arel onen yoshev*, even though like for example a זר
*zar* who does the עבודה avoda *avoda* in the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash. *Beit HaMikdash*, or a כהן kohein *kohen* who is טמא tamei,
*tamei*, or a כהן kohein *kohen* who is not wearing
the בגדי כהונה *bigdei kehuna*, all of those are מיתה בידי שמים
misa bidei shamayim. *misa bidei shamayim*. The following people who are not
allowed to do עבודה avoda. *avoda* in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash.
*Beit HaMikdash* is not מיתה בידי שמים misa bidei shamayim *misa bidei
shamayim*. ערל *Arel*, a כהן kohein *kohen* who is uncircumcised, even though
he's, רש"י *Rashi* always gives the example that he's from a family
of hemophiliacs, so he's not allowed to have a ברית מילה *brit
mila*. But whether he's doing that legally or illegally, anyway he's violating
the prohibition of,
either he's supposed to not have a ברית מילה *brit mila*, he's
a family from hemophiliacs, or he's violating. Either way, he's violating the
מצוה *mitzvah* ברית מילה *brit mila*. Nevertheless, in terms of the עבודה
avoda *avoda*, it's forbidden to do the עבודה avoda, *avoda* but it's
not חייב מיתה chayav misa. *chayav misa*. Or אונן *onen*, he is
in, he has just lost a close relative, he's in that period
of the day of death. Or יושב *yoshev*, he is sitting and
not standing. All of those, he invalidates the עבודה avodah *avoda* if
a כהן kohein *kohen* is in that situation, but it's not חייב
מיתה chayav mita *chayav misa*. באזהרה *Ba-azhara*, that is a negative prohibition
but it's not חייב מיתה chayav mitah, *chayav misa*. So let's take
a look at that. ערל מנלן *Arel minalan*, where do you know
this from ערל *arel*? אמר רב חסדא דבר זה מתורת משה רבינו
לא למדנו *Amar Rav Chisda davar ze mi-torat Moshe Rabbeinu lo lamadnu*.
We don't know this from משה'ס *Moshe's* תורה Torah *Torah*, that an
ערל *arel* is not allowed to do the עבודה avodah *avoda*, right?
Because there's two questions. A, how do you know it's prohibited, and
B, how is it not חייב chayav מיתה misa *chayav misa*. Okay,
so we don't know that it's prohibited from משה'ס *Moshe's* תורה Torah
*Torah*, עד שבא יחזקאל בן בוזי ולימדנו *ad she-ba Yechezkel ben Buzi
ve-limdanu*, until יחזקאל בן בוזי *Yechezkel ben Buzi* came along and taught
this to us. Right, this is always the big issue, that's why
they wanted to put יחזקאל *Yechezkel* in, they wanted to like, you
know, not include it in the canon, right, to be גונז *goneiz*
it because it has things in it that are not in the
תורה Torah *Torah*, sometimes they're in direct contradiction of the תורה Torah
*Torah*. But anyway, here we're sort of seeing this as not contradicting
but as in filling in a gap. What does it say in
יחזקאל *Yechezkel*? The meaning is there always also like, well presumably, right,
right. So presumably what we say is that it was always אסור
asur *assur* and then יחזקאל *Yechezkel* informed us of something that was
always there, except, you know, here it doesn't sound that way. It
says like, well maybe it says, it says we didn't learn it
from משה'ס *Moshe's* תורה *Torah*, but somehow an assumption that maybe it
was always the case. Okay, כל kol בן נכר ערל לב וערל
בשר לא יבוא אל מקדשי *kol ben nechar arel lev ve-arel basar
lo yavo el mikdashi*. Any foreigner who is either of an uncircumcised
heart, which means that he has basically committed apostasy, or that he
is of uncircumcised flesh, even if he has a legitimate reason not
to have a ברית מילה *brit mila*, he cannot serve in the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beit HaMikdash*. Okay, and it's interesting that it's
calling it a לאו lav. *lav*, a negative prohibition, because it's not
a negative prohibition in the תורה *Torah*, but we learn from יחזקאל
*Yechezkel* that it's forbidden. And anyway, since we're only learning it from
יחזקאל *Yechezkel*, clearly there's no basis to say that it's חייב chayav
מיתה mita? *chayav misa*. אונן מנלן *Onen minalan*, and how do you
know אונן *onen* is A, not allowed, but B, not חייב chayav
מיתה misa *chayav misa*? דכתיב *De-chtiv*, because a verse says, ומן המקדש
לא יצא ולא יחלל את מקדש mikdash אלהיו *u-min ha-mikdash lo yetzei
ve-lo yechalel et mikdash elohav*. This is by a כהן גדול *kohen
gadol*. When an immediate relative dies, he does not leave the Temple
and he does not desecrate, even though he is serving in the
Temple as an אונן *onen*, as somebody who's had an immediate relative
die upon him, that does not desecrate the sacrifices or the sanctuary.
Okay, so the implication is because he's a כהן גדול *kohen gadol*,
because he's supposed to remain in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beit
HaMikdash*. האחר *He-acher*, a different כהן *kohen* that would not have left
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beit HaMikdash* when he became an אונן
*onen*, חילל *chillel*, he would desecrate the sacrifices. Okay, now that doesn't
tell you it's a negative prohibition, but obviously it does, you know,
desecrate, violate. the services is invalid that was done. Okay, so אמרה
רב אדא בר אהבה לרבא *Amreh Rav Adda bar Ahava l'Rava*, so
implicitly obviously therefore it should not be done. אמרה רב אדא בר
אהבה לרבא ונילף חילול chilul חילול מתרומה *Amreh Rav Adda bar Ahava
l'Rava v'neilaf chilul chilul mitrumah*. So if it does sort of, you
know, desecrate and violate the service, maybe we should learn that it
is חייב chayav מיתה *chayav misa* from תרומה truma, *trumah*. Because from
תרומה truma *trumah* if a כהן *kohen* is טמא tamei *tamei* and
eats תרומה truma, *trumah*, he's חייב chayav מיתה *chayav misa*, and right
and there it says ולא יחללו *v'lo yechalelu*, that was a sort
of theme yesterday that that was the basis to tell you מיתה
בידי שמים misa bidei shamayim *misa b'yedei shamayim*. So here too if
there's חילול *chilul* it should be מיתה בידי שמים misa bidei shamayim
*misa b'yedei shamayim*. מה להלן במיתה אף כאן במיתה ma halan bemisa
af kan bemisa. *Mah halan b'misa af kan b'misa*, okay. No, so
the answer is מי כתיב ביה בגופיה *Mi ksiv bei b'gufei*? No,
no, it doesn't explicitly say that a normal כהן *kohen* who doesn't
leave when he's an אונן *onein* is מחלל *mechallel*. It's not explicit,
it's implicit. A כהן גדול *kohen gadol* who doesn't leave is not
מחלל *mechallel*. From there it's implicit that a normal כהן *kohen* is
מחלל *mechallel*. הא מכלל קאתי *Ha miklal ka ati*, I only learned
it out implicitly. הוי דבר הבא מן הכלל *Havi davar haba min
haklal*, it's something you learn out implicitly. וכל דבר הבא מן הכלל
אין דנין אותו בגזירה שוה *V'chol davar haba min haklal ein danin
oso b'gzeira shava*. And you can't make a גזירה שוה *gzeira shava*
of חילול חילול *chilul chilul* to tell you it's חייב chayav מיתה
*chayav misa*. Okay, now תוספות Tosafos *Tosfos* has a whole discussion, there
are times where we do learn it out from a גזירה שוה
*gzeira shava* even though it's implicit. But anyway, to implicitly we learn
out it's מחלל *mechallel*, presumably that's implicitly also enough to tell you
that it's לאו lav *lav*. Does לאו lav? *lav* mean a biblical
לאו *lav*, does it mean that obviously you shouldn't do it? Maybe
there's a biblical לאו *lav* because it says ולא יחלל את מקדש
mikdash אלהיו *v'lo yechalel es mikdash elohav*, right? So that means any
act that is מחלל *mechallel*, maybe that's a transgression of לא יחלל
*lo yechalel*. Okay, but nevertheless it is not explicit enough to say
it's חייב chayav. מיתה *chayav misa*. Okay, so that's ערל *areil* and
אונן *onein*. How about יושב *yoshev*? יושב מנלן *Yoshev minalan*? Where do
you know יושב *yoshev* is forbidden but at the same time you're
not חייב chayav מיתה *chayav misa*? יושב מנלן *Yoshev minalan*? אמר רבא
אמר רב נחמן אמר קרא *Amar Rava amar Rav Nachman amar kra*,
the verse says כי בו bo בחר ה' אלהיך מכל שבטיך לעמוד
לשרת *ki bo bachar Hashem elohecha mikol shvatecha la'amod l'shares*. You know,
he and the כהן גדול *kohen gadol* is chosen out of all
of the tribes, the כהנים kohanim *kohanim*, to stand to serve God.
לעמידה כתיבה ולא לישיבה *L'amida ksiva v'lo l'yeshiva*. The שירות *sheirus*, the
service in the temple, is done when it's בעמידה *b'amida*, not בישיבה
*b'yeshiva*. We get a bit of a לאו *lav* out of this.
Right? Again, so that's by all those. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s not
going out of its way to prove that it's a לאו *lav*,
although the language of the ברייתא braisa *braisa* said לאו *lav*. The
language of the ברייתא braisa *braisa* just might have meant you're not
supposed to do it. Okay. Also presumably it's מחלל העבודה *mechallel ha'avoda*,
but even with all of that, there is no basis to say,
it's not a strong enough basis to say that it's חייב מיתה
*chayav misa*. Does this mean you have to do it all over
again? I mean like say he did it. Yeah, that's what מחלל
העבודה *mechallel ha'avoda* means. Okay. בעל מום ba'al mum *baal mum*. Now,
how about the בעל מום ba'al mum *baal mum*? So that gets
back to actually our משנה Mishna *mishna*, I believe that was the
debate in our משנה Mishna *mishna*, right? It's interesting, right? Because our
משנה Mishna, *mishna* ended with this. No, our, excuse me, our משנה
mishna *mishna* was זר ששימש zar sheshimeish. *zar sheshimesh*. What's the, it's
interesting, right? Both the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* gets into a whole discussion
about the types of things that are חייב מיתה בידי שמים misa
bidei shamayim. *chayav misa b'yedei shamayim*, they're mostly temple related,
and it sort of our גמרא Gemara *Gemara* got into it as
a digression, but it ties into the theme of the last line
of our משנה mishna, *mishna* was also, right, seems completely out of
place, right? We were talking about things that קנאים פוגעים בו bo
*kanaim pogim bo*, and then we happened to mention oh what's the
story about a non-כהן *kohen* who does עבודה avodah *avoda*? You know,
that our משנה mishna *mishna* said רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva*
says it's חנק chenek *chenek* and the חכמים chachamim *chachamim* say it's
מיתה בידי שמים misa bidei shamayim *misa b'yedei shamayim*. Now, in our
משנה mishna *mishna* it wasn't a complete digression because one of the
cases which was similar to קנאים פוגעים בו bo *kanaim pogim bo*
was if a כהן טמא kohein tamei *kohen tamei* did the עבודה
*avoda*, the פרחי כהנים *perchi kohanim* would take him out and beat
him up with a, you know, with like a log, so they
killed him, till they beat,
you know, till they crushed his head. That was our משנה mishna
*mishna* for those who don't remember that.
Hard to forget that if you were here the other day. Anyway,
so somewhat in parallel we're discussing these things that are חייב מיתה
בידי שמים *chayav misa b'yedei shamayim*. So again, part like I said,
my theory is to round out the discussion of things that are
punishable by execution of the court, we're talking about things that are
חייב מיתה בידי שמים *chayav misa b'yedei shamayim*. Anyway, so in this
ברייתא Beraita. *braisa*, rather than the discussion about a non-כהן *kohen*, we
have the issue of a, what do you call it, of a
בעל
מום ba'al mum *baal mum*. What is the status of a בעל
מום ba'al mum *baal mum*? So רבי אומר במיתה Rebbe omer bemisa,
*Rebbi omer b'misa*, it's מיתה בידי שמים *misa b'yedei shamayim*. וחכמים אומרים
באזהרה *v'Chachamim omrim b'hazhara*, it's a לא תעשה *lo sa'asei*. So that
exactly parallels right the debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva*
and the חכמים chachamim *Chachamim* by a זר *zar*, this is the
debate of a בעל מום ba'al mum *baal mum*. So what is
this based on? מאי טעמא דרבי mai ta'ama deRebbe, *Mai ta'ama d'Rebbi*?
What's the reason of
Rebbi? So that it's מיתה בידי שמים *misa b'yedei shamayim*. דכתיב אל
הפרכת לא יבא ואל המזבח לא יגש כי מום
בו *diksiv el haparoches
lo yavo v'el hamizbeach lo yigash ki mum bo* ולא יחלל את
מקדשי *v'lo yechalel es mikdashai*
I
think it
is.
Okay,
so
this is
the בעל מום ba'al mum, *baal mum*, cannot
come into
the פרוכת *paroches*,
so,
you
know, into
the Holy
of Holies,
and cannot draw close
to the מזבח *mizbeach*,
okay, because he has a blemish,
and he shall not desecrate, be מחלל *mechallel*. ויליף חילול חילול מתרומה
*v'yalif chilul chilul mi-trumah* like we just said. Anytime you get the
word חילול *chilul*, that's a great basis now to learn out from
תרומה truma *trumah* that it's חייב מיתה *chayav misa*. מה להלן במיתה
אף כאן במיתה *Mah halan b'misa af kan b'misa*, okay. or כרת,
karet but it's not מיתה בידי שמיים. misa bidei shamayim. מה להלן
בכרת אף כאן בכרת. Ma halan bekares af kan bekares. So מסתברא,
mistavra, this is what the whole thing yesterday, whether when you have
חילול you learn it from תרומה, truma eating when you're eating תרומה
truma, when you're טמא, tamei. or you learn it from נותר, nosar,
and which one is it more similar to? So since most of
these, so let's take a look. So מסתברא מתרומה הווה ליה למילף.
mistavra mitruma hava lei lemilaf. It makes more sense to learn a
בעל מום ba'al mum. doing the עבודה from a כהן טמא kohein
tamei eating תרומה, truma שכן פסול הגוף, shekein psul hagoof, both of
them the problem is in the person. In one case the person
is טמא tamei, and in the other case the person is a
בעל מום ba'al mum? as opposed to the נותר, nosar, the problem
is in the food, not in the person. Okay, פסול הגוף מפסול
הגוף. psul hagoof mipsul hagoof. אדרבה מנותר הווה ליה למילף. adaraba minosar
hava lei lemilaf. No, let's learn out a case of a בעל
מום ba'al mum. from נותר, nosar, שכן קודש, shekein kodesh, okay, פנים,
pnim, that both of those are right in the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash, as opposed to תרומה truma, is out of the בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash It's פנים pnim which is sort of another way of
saying קודש. kodesh. It's in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash, Okay, פיגול
ונותר. pigul venosar. It's a, you know, it's in the realm in
which these are all really pretty much just variations of the בית
המקדש because a בעל מום ba'al mum doing the עבודה doesn't mean
that the problem is an object that's פיגול pigul or נותר. nosar.
He's doing, he's in the בית המקדש where פיגול pigul and נותר
nosar are like relevant concepts as opposed to תרומה truma. where they're
not. Okay, so anyway let's learn it out from נותר nosar which
is at least a more of a בית המקדש context. אלא מטמא
ששימש גמר. ela mitamei sheshimish gamar. Okay, so fine, we're not going
to learn it out from תרומה, truma תרומה truma, is clearly a
better basis to learn out a בעל מום ba'al mum from the
case of נותר, nosar, but we learn out something that is much
more comparable, a כהן who's not allowed to do the עבודה. So
one is a בעל מום, ba'al mum right, the other is a
כהן who is טמא. tamei. Okay, we could also have said a
כהן who doesn't have the בגדים, bgadim, right, yesterday was all these
כוהנים kohanim who can't do the עבודה and they are it's חייב
מיתה בידי שמיים. chayav misa bidei shamayim. Okay, so אלא מטמא ששימש,
ela mitamei sheshimish, גמר פסול הגוף מפסול הגוף. gamar psul hagoof mipsul
hagoof. Both of them are people that have a personal problem. Okay,
one is that he is טמא, tamei. the other is that he's
a בעל מום. ba'al mum קודש, kodesh, both of them are in
the בית המקדש, פנים, pnim, פיגול ונותר pigul venosar and they're like
again in the בית המקדש where these sacrifices are relevant. So obviously
that both has מקדש mikdash and a personal פסול psul and it's
more comparable than the case of נותר. nosar. Okay, so מקודש פנים
פיגול ונותר. mikodesh pnim pigul venosar. Okay, so that's all a very
nice basis. So they're basically saying look, if a כהן טמא kohen
tamei is חייב מיתה, a כהן בעל מום kohein ba'al mum is
חייב מיתה, that's pretty straightforward. ורבנן, verabanan, what do the rabbis say
back? אמר קרא בו. amar kra bo. It says ומתו בו כי
יחללהו. umesu bo ki yichaleluhu. בו ולא בבעל מום. bo velo beba'al
mum. Okay, so בו is a, is a limiting word, I think
it says this by תרומה, truma okay, and it says so he'll
die, yeah, by תרומה. truma. It says ומתו בו כי יחללהו. umesu
bo ki yichaleluhu. So בו seems as excluding. Now of course you
could have excluded anybody. Why did it exclude the בעל מום? ba'al
mum, Maybe it should have excluded the טמא. tamei Okay, so תוספות
Tosafot says a whole discussion why we've decided of all the things
that it excludes, it excludes a בעל מום. But the חכמים basically
say that no, all those other stuff we agree is מיתה בידי
שמיים, misa bidei shamayim, בעל מום not. It might be the difference
is that a בעל מום is אוכל את הקרבנות. ochel es hakorbanos.
A בעל מום is not as excluded as a טמא. tamei, Okay,
the תורה is explicit about that. It says that he is חלק
כחלק יאכלו, cheilek kecheilek yochalu, no, that's no, חלק כחלק cheilek kecheilek
is a different פסוק. pasuk. But anyway, but the תורה is explicit
that a בעל מום shares in the sacrifices after they're brought. So
maybe that's why חז"ל Chazal understood the רבנן, rabbanan, the rabbis here,
you know, understood that he's not as excluded as a טמא tamei
and it's not חייב מיתה. Okay, בו ולא בבעל מום. velo beba'al
mum. Okay, now המעיל במעילה. hame'il beme'ila. This, let's say somebody does
the איסור issur of gets הנאה hana'ah from the בית המקדש, you
know, from something sanctified במזיד. bemeizid. Now this interesting does tie back
to our משנה mishna because one of our cases in our משנה
mishna. of קנאים פוגעים בו was גונב את הקסוה gonev es hakisva
and קסוה kisva according to the גמרא Gemara. was some type of
a כלי שרת. kli shares. Now מעילה me'ila doesn't have to be
that you steal it, it could just be that you get הנאה
hana'ah from it, but anyway it's certainly in the same category. Okay,
so רבי Rebbi אומר במיתה, it's מיתה בידי שמיים misa bidei shamayim
וחכמים אומרים בלאו, vachachamim omrim belav, it's a negative prohibition. מאי טעמא
דרבי, אמר רב אבא אמר קרא בו, amar Rav Abba amar kra
bo, גמר חטא חטא מתרומה, gamar cheit cheit mitruma, מה להלן במיתה
אף כאן במיתה. So by מעילה me'ila it also says חטא, cheit,
it says וחטאה בשגגה מקדשי ה', vechata bishgaga mikodshei Hashem, okay, and
by תרומה terumah it says also, what's it say by תרומה, ולא
ישאו עליו חטא ומתו בו כי יחללהו. velo yisu alav cheit umesu
bo ki yichaleluhu. So the same way תרומה is מיתה בידי שמיים
misa bidei shamayim when it's טמא, this is also. וחכמים אמרי vachachamim
amri the same point. אמר קרא בו. amar kra bo. It says
בו by תרומה. ומתו בו כי יחללהו. umesu bo ki yichaleluhu. בו
ולא במעילה. bo velo beme'ila. Why of all the things should we
exclude מעילה me'ila and בעל מום, again, is not clear. Okay, the
last of this list takes us back to our משנה, mishna which
is a non-כהן who does the עבודה, זר ששימש במקדש. zar sheshimish
bemikdash. In our משנה mishna again what did you have? You had
that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said חנק chenek. and חכמים said מיתה
בידי שמים. Actually so it’s not exactly parallel. The recent debates were
מיתה בידי שמים or לאו. This is upscaling, it’s מיתה בידי שמים
or חנק. chenek. Okay. All right. So זר ששימש במקדש. zar sheshimeish
b'mikdash. So תניא דבי רבי ישמעאל אומר Tanya d'vei Rabbi Yishmael omer
נאמר כאן והזר הקרב יומת. ne'emar kan v'hazir hakarev yumat. So he
says here's a good question, it says shall die, does it mean
shall die by heaven or shall die by the court? So now
you understand why the choice here is either מיתה בידי שמים or
חנק. Chenek חנק chenek. was the סתם מיתה stam misa is חנק.
chenek. Okay. ונאמר להלן כל הקרב הקרב אל משכן ה' ימות, V'ne'emar
l'halan kol hakarev hakarev el mishkan Hashem yamut, that is by עדת
קרח. Adas Korach. לומר לך מה להלן בידי שמים Lomar lach mah
l'halan bidei shamayim the same way by קרח Korach they were saying
that when we draw close God is going to God killed those
because that was happening over there אף כאן בידי שמים. af kan
bidei shamayim. And you understand the reason to make the comparison because
they're both the same phenomenon, somebody who's not entitled to draw close
like a זר ששימש. zar sheshimeish So the חכמים say fine it
says יומת yumat but it means בידי שמים. רבי עקיבא אומר Rabbi
Akiva omer נאמר כאן והזר הקרב יומת ne'emar kan v'hazir hakarev yumat
ונאמר להלן והנביא ההוא או חולם החלום ההוא יומת. v'ne'emar l'halan v'hanavi
hahu o cholem hachalom hahu yumat. Okay these are both the same
word. Well that’s exactly the point although it’s a very different circumstance.
Okay so that’s the case of the נביא שקר. Navi Sheker. מה
להלן בסקילה אף כאן בסקילה Mah l'halan biskila af kan biskila which
isn't our משנה, mishna our משנה Mishnah said חנק. chenek רבי יונתן
בן נורי אומר Rabbi Yonatan ben Nuri omer מה להלן בחנק אף
כאן בחנק. mah l'halan b'chenek af kan b'chenek. So there's a debate
what a נביא שקר Navi Sheker gets, does he get חנק chenek
or does he get סקילה. skila. Okay so במאי קמיפלגי? b'mai kamifligi?
It's a three-way debate. What's the debate? רבי ישמעאל ורבי עקיבא. Rabbi
Yishmael v'Rabbi Akiva. So what's the debate of רבי ישמעאל ורבי עקיבא
Rabbi Yishmael v'Rabbi Akiva which is debate in our משנה Mishnah whether
it's put to death by the court or put to death by
God. רבי עקיבא סבר דנין יומת מיומת, Rabbi Akiva savar donin yumat
m'yumat, they both have the exact same word יומת. yumat. So it
says יומת yumat by the נביא שקר Navi Sheker that means בידי
בית דין bidei Beis Din so here too it means בית דין
Beis Din ואין דנין יומת מימות v'ein donin yumat m'yamut and you
don't learn it from ימות yamut by עדת קרח Adas Korach where
it’s not the same word. רבי ישמעאל סבר דנין הדיוט מהדיוט ואין
דנין הדיוט מנביא. Rabbi Yishmael savar donin hedyot m'hedyot v'ein donin hedyot
m'navi. No at least we'll learn a normal person who's doing the
עבודה from a normal person. We're not going to compare it to
a case of a נביא. navi. What you also could have said
is of course that and maybe that’s what it means by הדיוט
מהדיוט hedyot m'hedyot is that that was essentially the same thing, people
that should not have been doing the עבודה were doing the עבודה
and they died by God's hands and therefore we'll say the same
thing here. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would say back to you כיון
שהדיח אין לך הדיוט גדול מזה. keivan she'hidiach ein lecha hedyot gadol
mizeh. Since the נביא navi is pushing people off from the path
okay that he isn't a נביא navi if anything he's like a
נביא שקר. Navi Sheker. That's not a נביא navi he's just purporting
to be a נביא. navi. Okay but the point I think still
isn't is he a real נביא navi or not a real נביא
navi but it's a completely different thing whereas רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
says the same type of sin is מיתה בידי שמים. Okay. Now
במאי קמיפלגי רבי עקיבא ורבי יונתן בן נורי? b'mai kamifligi Rabbi Akiva
v'Rabbi Yonatan ben Nuri? What's the debate about whether it gets סקילה
skila or whether it gets חנק chenek. assuming that it is going
to be punishable by the court. Okay it is pretty interesting right
because is this the only case where everything we really learn about
like a sin in the context of the מקדש mikdash was never
punishable by death by the court? Right would this be like the
only one? I mean yeah like I can't think of another case
of a sin in the מקדש mikdash right even like if you're
טמא and you're נכנס nichnas into the מקדש it's a חיוב כרת.
chiyuv kares. So it's pretty radical to think that it's מיתה בידי
בית דין misa bidei Beis Din right? Okay so anyway so okay
so what's that debate? הפלוגתא דרבי שמעון ורבנן דתניא. haplugta d'Rabbi Shimon
v'Rabanan d'tanya. So they both agree we learn from a נביא שקר
Navi Sheker the question is what does a נביא שקר Navi Sheker
get? נביא שהדיח בסקילה Navi shehidiach biskila רבי שמעון אומר בחנק. Rabbi
Shimon omer b'chenek. So the רבנן Rabanan say it's סקילה skila and
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says it's חנק. chenek. So that would be
the debate whether this person who we learn from the נביא navi
also gets סקילה skila or gets חנק. chenek. So הגמרא hag'mora says
והנן תנן רבי עקיבא אומר בחנק. v'hanan tenan Rabbi Akiva omer b'chenek.
Okay but this ברייתא has רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva saying סקילה. skila.
Our משנה Mishnah, has רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva. saying חנק. chenek So
הגמרא hag'mora says תרי תנאי אליבא דרבי עקיבא. trei tannai aliba d'Rabbi
Akiva. Fine it's a debate what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said. So
מתניתין רבי שמעון אליבא דרבי עקיבא. masnisin Rabbi Shimon aliba d'Rabbi Akiva.
Our משנה Mishnah. is רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon who said that it
gets חנק chenek and that would be saying it in the name
because his רבי was רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva So according to רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon who says חנק chenek. he's understanding that רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva would say חנק. chenek. That's our משנה. ברייתא רבנן אליבא
דרבי עקיבא. Braisa Rabanan aliba d'Rabbi Akiva. And our ברייתא is other
students of רבי עקיבא who said that according to רבי עקיבא you
get סקילה. skila. מכל מקום Mikol makom it is quite interesting right
on the one hand that a כהן טמא that was שימש shimeish
his fellow כהנים would take him out and kill him and beat
his head in and a זר ששימש according to some actually gets
מיתה by the court right? So this is again that's quite radical
when you think about all these other things are מיתה בידי שמים
and I think this is the one sort of מקדש related thing
that is actually you know בידי אדם. bidei adam. הדרן עלך אלו
הן הנשרפין. Hadran alach elu hen hanisrafin. Yes Michael question. We're going
to cover this, we just covered, but I'm having a hard time
just wrapping my mind around this כיפה kippa thing. We've had all
these things that, you know, בכולהו מיתה יפה? be-chulhu mita yaffa? Right?
And you know, ובזה אין לך מיתה מנוולת מזו? u-vizeh ein lecha
mita menuvelet mizu? Yeah, somebody raised that. Like again, I don't know,
I mean all I said was was that according to the פשט
pshat of the of the משנה and the, you know, the ירושלמי
Yerushalmi never has this idea that he dies. The פשט pshat of
the משנה is not that he dies, the פשט pshat of the
משנה is just you put him in prison. And that the whole
difference between לחם צר ומים לחץ lechem tzar u-mayim lachatz by שעורין
se'orin and מים לחץ mayim lachatz is that לחם צר ומים לחץ
lechem tzar u-mayim lachatz is figurative. It means that the murderer you
give bare rations, bread and, you know, small measures of bread and
water, whereas the person who was the person who was a repeat
offender, you give him as much barley as he wants to eat.
It's just figurative. It doesn't literally mean you bring about the death,
right? It's really just the בבלי, Bavli, the סתמא stama of the
בבלי Bavli that chooses to read the two משניות mishnayot together and
to read it that way. But within that reading, right, then it
is, yes, it is very strange, and it's a very disfiguring thing.
It's also very strange also that we would choose to do it,
the other point I made is that it says like if some
one of the reasons it said that we can't execute the murderer
is because we tripped up the witnesses on asking these like very
superfluous בדיקות bedikot to trip them up. So what's the point? We
trip them up with asking these I mean these extra, excuse me,
חקירה בדיקה, chakira bedika, right, in order to get them to trip
up so we don't have to execute the guy, and then we
go ahead and we kill him anyway. We might as well just
execute him in the court in order to get כפרה. kappara. You
know, why are we if we're going to bring him so, it
seems like well we don't want to get our hands dirty. We
want him to die but we don't want to be the ones
to do it. But you're right, it is very strange according to
that, that it's that very disfiguring type of a thing. Okay, so
yes? Which punishment is worse? Punishment by the court or punishment by
Heaven? I mean is there a... Well, punishment, I mean, I mean
punishment by the court you actually get, you actually die. I mean,
I think like and... Yeah, I mean, I think the general assumption
is that something that's חייב מיתה בידי בית דין chayav mita bidei
beit din is a weightier sin than חייב מיתה בידי שמיים. chayav
mita bidei shamayim. But the interesting question is, but if the guy
then actually is executed by בית דין, beit din, does that achieve
כפרה kappara whereas the חיוב מיתה בידי שמיים chiyuv mita bidei shamayim
wouldn't? Of course, the guy who's חייב מיתה בידי שמיים chayav mita
bidei shamayim could always do תשובה teshuva and then he would be
forgiven, you know? But so but the general assumption is that a
sin that's חייב מיתה בידי בית דין chayav mita bidei beit din
is weightier than חייב מיתה בידי שמיים. chayav mita bidei shamayim. Okay,
what the consequences like after the sin is a different question after
the עונש onesh in terms of of כפרה kappara is a different
question. Is כרת karet the same as מיתה בידי שמיים? mita bidei
shamayim? No. So that's important, right? Because the גמרא Gemara here actually
just explicitly distinguished that as well for example by... where where was
it actually distinguishing כרת karet from מיתה? I think it was by
מעילה? Me'ilah? Was it... No, yeah, by נותר. notar. נותר notar is
כרת karet and that was contrasted to תרומה which is מיתה בידי
שמיים. mita bidei shamayim. So, yeah, it's not fully spelled out. כרת
karet is understood to mean like probably like a foreshortened life, whereas
like the גמרא Gemara says like people who die, you know, you
know, in their fifties or whatever, it's like a מיתת כרת. mitat
karet. But if like or כרת וערירי karet ve-ariri is childless, but
it's but מיתה בידי שמיים mita bidei shamayim is seen as harsher,
maybe more like immediate. Again, it doesn't actually happen immediately to the
best that we can tell, but you know, but כרת karet, is
right is not, yes, מיתה בידי שמיים mita bidei shamayim is definitely
seen as worse. It's like כרת, כרת וערירי, karet ve-ariri, מיתה בידי
שמיים, mita bidei shamayim, and then מיתת בית דין. mitat beit din.
Like that sort of seems to be the hierarchy. Okay, let's take
a look now as we turn to this next פרק. perek. Now,
so we've gone through סקילה ושריפה, sekila ve-sreifa, what we did, you
know, סקילה שריפה הרג. sekila sreifa hereg. הרג hereg was included in
אלו הן הנשרפין, Elu Hen Ha-Nisrafin, if you remember. הרג hereg was
the רוצח, rotzeach, and that led us into well, within the well
first of all the סקילה sekila thing led us into a whole
discussion of בן סורר ומורה ben sorer u-moreh and led us into
a whole case about רודף like the הרג hereg thing about the
רוצח rotzeach led us into a whole fascinating discussion about defining רציחה
retzicha and then also defining these interesting cases about like a רוצח
rotzeach that gets mixed up and cases about קנאין פוגעין בו. kana'im
pog'in bo. So we have all these like and then we got
into this whole מיתה בידי שמיים, mita bidei shamayim, these attendant things.
And now we're left with like the last category which is חנק.
chenek. Okay? And אלו הן הנחנקין. Elu Hen Ha-Nechnakin. And then the
final last פרק perek is חלק. Chelek. חלק Chelek is all ישראל
has a חלק לעולם הבא chelek l'olam haba except for those who
don't. But the basic implication being, but the implication being that even
the people who did these terrible sins, right, and got all these
מיתות בית דין mitot beit din exactly ties into the point that
we were just discussing about like about that, you know, okay the
person got a מיתת בית דין mitat beit din but eventually they'll
have a חלק לעולם הבא. chelek l'olam haba. It's only the few
people that don't have a חלק לעולם הבא chelek l'olam haba and
that certainly seems to be the natural progression of the פרקים. prakim.
Right? You go through the ארבע מיתות arba mitot with appropriate digressions.
Okay? And then you have a whole discussion, this aggadic discussion about
who has a חלק לעולם הבא. chelek l'olam haba. Interestingly, the ירושלמי
Yerushalmi reverses the order. The ירושלמי Yerushalmi has חלק chelek first and
אלו הנחנקים eilu hanechenakim last. And I have to tell you I
don't really understand it. Like why after a discussion of the נשרפין
nisrafin and whatever and שריפה sreifa and הרג, hereg, right, and these
even these digression cases, why should that lead into a discussion of
who has a חלק לעולם הבא chelek l'olam haba and then we
double back to talk about אלו הן הנחנקים? eilu hen hanechenakim? Not
only that, many פרקים, prakim, many מסכתות masechtos end with some type
of an אגדתא aggadic ending, okay, and the end of חלק chelek
which is all of חלק chelek is pretty אגדתא, aggadic, but the
end of it also is a nice sort of אגדתא aggadic ending
when we'll see, a nice ending to the whole מסכת, maseches, whereas
אלו הן הנחנקים eilu hen hanechenakim just ends with a some technical
הלכה halachic discussion about חנק. chenek. So again, this order we have,
people do note that the ירושלמי Yerushalmi has a different order, but
this order to me I have a very hard time understanding how
the other order makes any sense. This order really does make sense.
Yes. I read that מכות Makos actually was originally part of סנהדרין.
Sanhedrin. That is true too. So how does חלק chelek go before?
That's true. I mean, in terms of the question of does it
have an appropriate ending or not, if מכות Makos because מכות Makos
does have an אגדתא aggadic ending, and so if you put מכות
Makos together with סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, right, that sort of does address that
point. But anyway, as we'll see, you can tell me if you
think that the order of the פרקים prakim should be reversed from
the way we have it, okay, whether you like the בבלי Bavli
order or the ירושלמי Yerushalmi order better. Anyway, we're going to follow
the בבלי. Bavli. Let's take a look. אלו הן הנחנקים. eilu hen
hanechenakim. So we've done all the three, now we're to the catchall
which is חנק. chenek. So because it's the catchall you think it's
a pretty big category, but it's really, because any default מיתה is
חנק. chenek. But let's see, it's not that huge. Okay, המכה אביו
ואמו, hamakeh aviv v'imo, person who hits father and mother, makes a
wound. וגונב נפש מישראל, v'gonev nefesh m'Yisrael, somebody who kidnaps. וזקן ממרא,
v'zaken mamre, so that's going to be fun, it's going to be
an opportunity to explore the category of זקן ממרא, zaken mamre, right?
Some of these some of these sins don't have an opportunity to
get explored anywhere else in ש"ס. Shas. Okay, על פי בית דין,
al pi beis din, meaning that you reject the central court of
the בית דין. beis din. ונביא השקר, v'navi hasheker, the false prophet,
okay, והמתנבא בשם עבודת כוכבים, v'hamisnabbe b'shem avodas kochavim, and somebody that
prophesies in the name of עבודה זרה. avoda zara. So one is
prophesying in the name of a god but a false prophet, and
the other is prophesying in the name of עבודה זרה. avoda zara.
והבא על אשת איש, v'haba al eishet ish, adultery, straight case of
adultery, we've had that often with the עריות arayos as the contrast,
adultery was חנק. chenek, וזוממי בת כהן ובועלה. v'zommei bas kohen u'voalah.
So a בת כהן, bas kohen, different argument which category, type of
בת כהן, bas kohen, נערה מאורסה, naarah me'urasah, נשואה, nesuah, whatever, but
anyway we do know that there's a בת כהן bas kohen that
gets שריפה. sreifa. Nevertheless, the דרשה drasha is את אביה היא מחללת
באש תשרף, es aviha hi mechaleles ba'eish tisareif, היא באש תשרף ואין
בועלה באש תשרף. hi ba'eish tisareif v'ein boalah ba'eish tisareif. That the
man who has intercourse with her doesn't get שריפה, sreifa, he would
get whatever he would get if she weren't a בת כהן, bas
kohen, so assuming that otherwise if she weren't a בת כהן bas
kohen it would be חנק, chenek. the man gets חנק. chenek. And
similarly if they're עדים זוממים eidim zomemim that say that she committed
this act, okay, even if they would also get חנק. chenek Now
you could say maybe they're getting חנק chenek, because they're also testifying
against the man. But let's say they say we don't know who
the man is, okay, we're some stranger, we're not testifying against the
man, we're here only to testify against her. Nevertheless, even though what
they're trying to do to her is give her שריפה, sreifa, they
would get חנק, chenek? again, based on היא באש תשרף hi ba'eish
tisareif and also based on the פסוק pasuk כאשר זמם לעשות לאחיו,
ka'asher zamam la'asos l'achiv, לאחיו ולא לאחותו. l'achiv v'lo l'achoso. So this
is the one case where it's a punishment that is specifically to
her and to nobody else, even people you would assume would have
a similar punishment as she does. Okay, so let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara We're going to go through each one individually.
Okay, המכה אביו ואמו מנלן? hamakeh aviv v'imo minalan? How do you
know המכה אביו ואמו hamakeh aviv v'imo gets חנק? chenek. דכתיב מכה
אביו ואמו מות יומת. dichtiv makeh aviv v'imo mos yumas. Okay, וכל
מיתה v'chol misa put to death האמורה בתורה סתם ha'amurah baTorah stam
אינה אלא חנק. eina ela chenek. If you don't have any other
category, the generic category is חנק. chenek. So now the גמרא Gemara
says how do you know it's not like some fifth thing we
haven't thought of? Because we discussed that way back when we did
the first discussion of the ארבע מיתות. arba misos. Okay, and so
the גמרא Gemara says אימא עד דקטל ליה מקטלא. eima ad d'katil
lei miktala. Now how do you know המכה hamakeh means to just
hit? Maybe המכה hamakeh means to hit and to kill. Okay, so
you know if you kill a normal person that's הרג, hereg, and
if somebody kills a father or mother it's חנק. chenek? So the
גמרא Gemara says no. So the גמרא Gemara says סלקא דעתך עד
דקטל ליה? salka dach'tach ad d'katil lei? Excuse me, maybe it means
killing him. מקטלא סלקא דעתך? miktala salka dach'tach? It means killing him?
קטיל חד בסייף אביו בחנק? katil chad b'sayaf aviv b'chenek? If somebody
kills a normal person he gets the sword and the father it's
חנק? chenek I mean the father should be a worse punishment. This
would make it a lighter punishment. So the גמרא Gemara says הניחא
למאן דאמר חנק קל. hani'cha l'man d'amar chenek kal. That's good if
you assume that חנק chenek is a lighter death than obviously this
can't mean just to kill a father because it wouldn't be a
lighter. lighter punishment than killing somebody else. אלא למאן דאמר חנק חמור
ela le-man de-amar chenek chamur but if חנק chenek is weightier than
סייף, sayif, מאי איכא למימר, mai ika le-meimar, right? רב שמעון, Reb
Shimon, what could you say? Because אין הכי נמי, ein hachi nami,
kill a normal person it's סייף, sayif, father it's a worse punishment,
it's חנק according to רב שמעון. Reb Shimon. So how do you
know מכה אביו ואמו makeh aviv v'imo doesn't mean to kill? How
do you know it just means to hit? אלא מדכתיב מכה איש
ומת מות יומת ela midichtiv makeh ish v'meis mos yumas because when
the תורה wants to say you kill someone, it says you kill
them. It doesn't just say you hit them. It says מכה איש
ומת. makeh ish v'meis. If you kill somebody you put them to
death. ואחסה מיתה ומיסו מכולו, ve-achasa mitah ve-misu m'kulu, fine but that's
clear from context. וכתיב או באיבה הכהו בידו וימות u-chtiv o b'eivah
hikahu b'yado vayamus or he smote him with anger and he died.
שמע מינה כל היכא דכתיב הכה סתם לאו מיתה היא. shema mina
kol heicha de-chtiv hakah stam lav mitah hi. If there's no context
that makes it clear, simple hitting does not mean killing. Based on
that we know that means just to hit the father is put
to death. ואיצטריך למיכתב מכה איש ואיצטריך למיכתב כל מכה נפש. ve-itztarich
lemichtav makeh ish ve-itztarich lemichtav kol makeh nefesh. Now we're digressing a
little bit back to the murder discussion. When it comes to murder,
why does it have to say מכה איש makeh ish and why
does it say כל מכה נפש? kol makeh nefesh? למכתב מכה איש
ואיצטריך למימר מכה נפש. lemichtav makeh ish ve-itztarich le-meimar makeh nefesh. אי
כתב רחמנא מכה איש ומת, ei katav rachmana makeh ish v'meis, a
kill a man, הוה אמינא איש דבר מצווה אין קטן לא, hava
amina ish bar mitzvah in katan lo, only a man who is
fully obligated in מצוות, mitzvot, not a minor. Interesting, you wonder what
the point would be about a woman. תוספות says actually there are
some גרסאות girsa'ot that say maybe I would think a woman who's
partly exempt from מצוות mitzvot would be excluded, but that's not our
גרסא. girsa. Our גרסא girsa is maybe only a man, meaning only
an adult and not a minor. קטן לא. katan lo. כתב רחמנא
כל מכה נפש, katav rachmana kol makeh nefesh, any smiting of any
soul, doesn't have to be an adult. ואי כתב רחמנא כל מכה
נפש הוה אמינא אפילו נפלים. ve-ei katav rachmana kol makeh nefesh hava
amina afilu nefalim. If it's maybe even a soul, maybe even not
yet a full person, maybe even if it's a fetus, אפילו בן
שמונה afilu ben shemona or a child born in the eighth month
that's not considered to be viable and that presumably also would have
read it as מכה כל נפש, makeh kol nefesh, probably reading the
כל to modify the נפש nefesh as well. וצריכי, u-tzrichi, so therefore
it has to say איש, ish, that the person is considered to
be born and viable, even if not an adult. ואימא אף על
גב דלא עביד בה חבורה. ve-eima af al gav d'la avid bah
chabura. Fine, so that's just parenthetical about murder, what those two פסוקים
pesukim are. But back to father, since מכה makeh does not mean
to kill, maybe מכה makeh means any hitting, even without making a
wound? Now we haven't said yet it's a wound, but the next
משנה is going to say it's a wound. If you just peek,
if you want to take a peek at the next משנה on
the top of פה עמוד ב, peh amud bet, it's המכה אביו
ואמו אינו חייב עד שיעשה בהן חבורה, hamakeh aviv v'imo eino chayav
ad she-ya'aseh bahen chabura, until you make a wound. So now we
want to know how that's true. ה גמרא the Gemara says like
this, ואימא אף על גב דלא עביד בה חבורה, ve-eima af al
gav d'la avid bah chabura, maybe even if you don't make a
wound. אלמה תנן, almah tnan, why did we teach in a משנה,
המכה אביו ואמו אינו חייב עד שיעשה בהן חבורה? hamakeh aviv v'imo
eino chayav ad she-ya'aseh bahen chabura? That's our next משנה. How do
you know that? אמר קרא מכה אדם ומכה בהמה. amar kra makeh
adam u-makeh behema. It says מכה נפש בהמה ישלמנה נפש תחת מכה
אדם יומת. makeh nefesh behema yeshalmena nefesh tachat makeh adam yumat. Right,
so it exactly compares them. Now we remember that that comparison has
been quoted a lot to speak about קים ליה בדרבה מיניה, kim
leh b'drabbah mineh, that anytime a person is murdered, even maybe if
the murderer is not put to death or whatever, there's not going
to be any monetary payment. But let's see what we do with
it here. מכה אדם ומכה בהמה, makeh adam u-makeh behema, מה מכה
בהמה עד דעביד בה חבורה, mah makeh behema ad d'avid bah chabura,
the same way a בהמה behema you only have to pay damages
if you actually wound the animal, דכתיב בנפש. dichtiv benefesh. How do
you know? Because it says מכה נפש בהמה makeh nefesh behema and
נפש nefesh often means like blood. כי הדם הוא בנפש יכפר. ki
ha-dam hu ba-nefesh yechaper. So therefore נפש בהמה nefesh behema means that
somehow blood came out or at least it caused some clotting of
blood and so on, some like a wound that obviously showed that
blood at least came out underneath the skin, so there's a redness
in the wound and so on. So the same way by בהמה
behema it obviously means that there's some blood, אף מכה אדם עד
דעביד בה חבורה. af makeh adam ad d'avid bah chabura. That's how
we know that and therefore the מכה אדם makeh adam here is
being used as just מכה, makeh, without killing the person, מכה אדם
יומת makeh adam yumat we said means אביו ואמו, aviv v'imo, a
parent, because there's no what do you call? Because it's excuse me,
one פסוק pasuk is explicit, one פסוק pasuk says, what the גמרא
Gemara isn't saying here, excuse me, מכה אביו ואמו מות יומת. makeh
aviv v'imo mos yumas. So there we know you're put to death,
and we say that the מכה makeh means even without killing. Now
this is the punishment. Another פסוק pasuk says מכה נפש בהמה ישלמנה
ומכה אדם יומת. makeh nefesh behema yeshalmena u-makeh adam yumat. So we
could say that this מכה makeh means to kill. But again, we've
just got through saying that מכה makeh without saying anything specific doesn't
mean to kill. So we're going to assume that this also is
talking about smiting a parent the same way this is talking about
smiting a parent. By the way, what we don't have yet is
a פסוק pasuk that tells you you're not allowed to do it.
Okay, we just have two פסוקים pesukim that tell you the punishment.
But presumably we're saying both this and this was without killing, so
they're this is also about parent, okay, and the same way here
the נפש nefesh is about causing blood to come out, here too,
by killing the by hitting the parent, it's only by causing blood
to come out. I'm sorry, because if it wouldn't have been נפש
nefesh you would have thought meaning yeah because then you would have
been חייב for causing injury without blood coming out which any נפש
nefesh yes which anyway is but what the גמרא Gemara asks since
when are you only חייב if you damage somebody's animal if blood
comes out? What if you damage their animal without blood coming out,
which is what the גמרא'ס Gemara's about to ask. Yes. So there's
no you don't just hitting a normal person not put to death
hitting a normal person is a לאו right and if you know
what that seems like a exactly exactly so this is never read
as hitting a normal person. It's either read as as killing a
normal person or it's read as hitting a parent. Okay. So okay
so מתיב ליה רב ירמיה לרב ירמיה קאמרת הכי אלא מעתה הכישה
באבנים הכי נמי דלא מיחייב? Masiv lei Rav Yirmiyah le-Rav Yirmiyah ka-amrat
hachi ella me-ata hikishah ba-avanim hachi nami de-lo michayev? Let's say I
go ahead and I throw stones at Michael's Michael's בהמה behemah right
exactly I I and no there's no visible wound. Okay let's say
I manage to break the bones in Michael's cow there without making
any visible wound and without any blood coming out okay and I
make it worthless you know and are you going to tell me
I don't have to pay Michael? Of course I have to pay
Michael that's מזיק. mazik. Okay so obviously so whatever נפש nefesh means
it does not mean that for a בהמה behemah you need to
cause a wound to be חייב for מזיק. mazik. So so אלא
מעתה הכישה באבנים הכי נמי דלא מיחייב? Ella me-ata hikishah ba-avanim hachi
nami de-lo michayev? אלא Ella fine you're right you know what you
don't need to cause a wound in a בהמה behemah to have
to pay. So what is the נפש nefesh doing? אם אינו עניין
לנפש בהמה דהא אינמי בהכישה באבנים חייב Im eino inyan le-nefesh behemah
de-ha inami be-hikishah ba-avanim chayav as you just pointed out you don't
need to wound a בהמה behemah to have to pay if you
made it worthless. So what is the נפש nefesh doing? It's not
coming to tell you a הלכה halachah in damaging an animal. So
תנהו עניין לנפש אדם. Tenahu inyan le-nefesh adam. Okay you're absolutely correct
this נפש nefesh it's not like it's true by a בהמה behemah
that's also true by אדם. adam. It's actually not true by a
בהמה. behemah. By בהמה behemah you don't I have no idea by
a בהמה behemah you don't need to cause blood to come out.
So what's it doing? It's really here for the אדם adam purpose
okay it's really here to tell you that when you smite a
person and maybe if it would have said מכה נפש אדם makkeh
nefesh adam you would have said it meant murder so we want
מכה אדם makkeh adam to not mean murder we want it to
mean smiting a parent so we don't have נפש nefesh here we
have נפש nefesh here but the נפש nefesh here's telling you that
this thing is causing blood to come out. Now by the way
just sort of describing it that way you do understand that at
least figuratively the point that's being made is is that the smiting
of a parent is some type of a quasi seen as like
a quasi murder right like that some blood come out it's representative
of that. By the way the whole point that by שבת Shabbos
right that why you're חייב by שבת Shabbos when you cause you
know blood to come out of something make a wound right it's
learned from נטילת נשמה netilat neshamah from שוחט shochet from שוחט shochat
an animal. Okay so the whole idea of the blood and the
wounding and whatever it's sort of like a mini murder. So that
seems at least to be what we're saying by the parent. By
the way the ירושלמי Yerushalmi has an interesting question. It wants to
know if the חבורה chaburah that we say by a parent is
like the חבורה chaburah of שבת Shabbos or like the חבורה chaburah
of מזיק. mazik. Now we just said that מזיק mazik doesn't need
a חבורה. chaburah. Okay but what presumably what the ירושלמי seems to
be saying is it might not need a חבורה chaburah but it
needs permanent damage. If I go ahead and beat somebody beat somebody
up or beat up somebody's animal and the well I guess the
person's beat somebody up because an animal what I'm going to say
isn't relevant. If I go ahead and I beat somebody up and
there's no permanent damage then I don't pay נזק. nezek. I pay
שבת shevet I pay the amount of time they're out of work
I pay ריפוי ripui I pay the doctor's bill I pay צער
tza'ar I pay the pain but נזק nezek is only for permanent
damage. So the ירושלמי has a question that maybe the חבורה chaburah
by a father or a mother is it just that there's some
blood that comes out which seems to be or even some blood
that what is it coagulates or whatever anyway under under the skin
that certainly seems to be the פשט pshat okay as we'll see
in a minute that any blood is is in this category but
the ירושלמי seems to have a הוה אמינא hava amina that it
might only be if it's a permanent damage not if it's a
not if it's a something that will just heal. Okay because it
is let's face it you know like the גמרא Gemara get all
got all worked up about בן סורר ומורה Ben Sorer U-Moreh how
could it be just because this guy's a בן סורר ומורה Ben
Sorer U-Moreh we put him to death? And at the same time
somebody curses a father or mother or hits a father or mother
and causes a little blood to come out that we have no
problem putting the person to death right? So you know I don't
so anyway but at least you know it seems like it's least
this case is seen as some type of a figurative murder. Okay
so let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay so the גמרא Gemara says like this אי נמי תנהו עניין
לנפש אדם אלא היקישא למה לי? Ei nami tenahu inyan le-nefesh adam
ella he-keisha lamma li? So if you're going to just borrow the
נפש nefesh so it's so what is the point of comparing the
two right it's not to learn out this principle of wounding... with
blood because that's not learned out by the comparison, that's just learned
by the extra word. So אלא היקשא למה לי? ela hekesha lama
li? What's learned out by the comparison? וכדתניא, ukhedetanya, like we taught
in the ברייתא. וכדתניא דבי חזקיה, ukhedetanya devei Chizkiya, like d'bei Chizkiya
teaches, which is what is that if there's a death penalty, there
even if it's not במזיד bemezid and you're not going to execute
the person, there's not going to be any financial payment. So the
גמרא Gemara says הניחא למאן דאית ליה תנא דבי חזקיה. hani nicha
leman de'it leh tana devei Chizkiya. That's good if you hold of
תנא דבי חזקיה. tana devei Chizkiya. אלא למאן דלית ליה תנא דבי
חזקיה, ela leman deleit leh tana devei Chizkiya, we learned before perhaps
some people don't hold like him across the board. So היקשא למה
לי? hekesha lama li? Why are we connecting smiting a person whether
it's a parent or whether it's killing a person to wounding an
animal? So מה מכה בהמה לרפואה פטור אף מכה אדם לרפואה פטור.
ma maka behema lirfua patur af maka adam lirfua patur. To tell
you a הלכה halacha within wounding a parent. The same way if
I go ahead and I do some surgery on Michael's cow, I'm
פטור, patur, okay, for wounding, I don't have to pay him for
damage, okay. Similar now of course an interesting question, let's say I
was trying to help Michael's cow and accidentally I hurt it, right?
That gets to a whole question of malpractice, okay, which is a
whole discussion in בבא מציעא Bava Metzia or whatever about אומן שקלקל
uman shekilkel and so on, okay, but at least there are cases
where I don't have to pay even even if I caused accidental
damage and certainly if I helped Michael's cow by doing a surgery.
So therefore somebody who wounds a parent in the context of רפואה
refua does not have to pay. איבעיא להו ibaia lehu because we
raise the question, בן מהו שיקיז דם לאביו? ben mahu sheyakiz dam
le'aviv? Can a father let a son let blood for the father?
Right? So this is actually actively causing a wound but it's for
the purpose of healing. So רב מתנא אמר ואהבת לרעך כמוך. Rav
Matna amar ve'ahavta lere'acha kamocha. Yes, from ואהבת לרעך כמוך, ve'ahavta lere'acha
kamocha, which is pretty amazing. Here you have an עבירה aveira which
is חייב מיתה and you're going to use some generic פסוק pasuk
which like can you know it's so generic it applies to everything
in this world but because it applies to everything also like to
some degree like it applies to nothing, right? So it's this completely
generic פסוק pasuk of ואהבת לרעך כמוך ve'ahavta lere'acha kamocha and we're
going to say, oh, that's going to tell you that you're not
חייב for מכה אביו ואמו. maka aviv ve'imo. But it is interesting
sometimes that we use that type of a principle to guide like
you know מצוות בין אדם לחבירו, mitzvot bein adam lechavero, you know,
things like there are some general ethical principles like ואהבת לרעך כמוך,
ve'ahavta lere'acha kamocha, חייך קודמין לחיי חבירך, chayecha kodmin lechayei chavercha, but
these types of things which are like sometimes guide explicit לאוין. lavin.
Like I said, you know, like for example, there's a prohibition like
לא תקם ולא תטר את בני עמך, lo tikom velo titor et
benei amecha, right? Don't take vengeance. But the גמרא Gemara. says like
you know כל תלמיד חכם שאינו נוקם ונוטר כנחש kol talmid chacham
she'eino nokem venoter kenachash like a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham has to
be you know very you know vengeful because it's defending Torah's honor,
right? Or there's a prohibition to hit somebody but then you know
the according... the גמרא Gemara allowed a father to hit his son
or a rabbi to hit a student, you know, or something like
that. Like how do we know those things? Right? I mean these
are explicit לאוין. lavin. Where do we know to allow these types
of cases, right? So it does seem somehow that because they're also
even though they're prohibitions, because they're prohibitions in somehow the interpersonal realm,
we allow certain like ethical guidelines. I mean again, we might not
exactly identify with the idea of hitting a child, but okay, but
you know, the גמרא's Gemara sort of understanding of like what are
those proper interpersonal interactions to guide and define the shape of this
explicit prohibition and not to read it categorically, right? Like we would
if this was a ritual thing, we would read it much more
probably categorically than if it's a type of an interpersonal one where
we can sort of be guided by this principle. So that's quite
interesting. We use ואהבת לרעך כמוך ve'ahavta lere'acha kamocha to tell you
clearly מכה אביו ואמו maka aviv ve'imo doesn't apply to this case.
Yes. Isn't it just a sense of consent? I mean obviously it's
with the father's consent that he's letting the blood, right? Yeah, but
again, that's well that... it's a similar point, you know, but since
when do we know that the תורה would say that that wouldn't
apply in a case of consent? Right? So you mean the whole
idea of מכה maka maybe the word מכה maka itself implicitly means,
right, so what you're saying is a better point, which is not
just a consent point, but it's not מכה. maka. מכה maka is
a word that sort of is a you know is a violation
of me, right? This is actually a surgical procedure. It's not defined
as a הכאה. haka'ah. Right? So right. So that's like a good
point, okay. I mean you could have cases where it's with consent
but it's still a הכאה. haka'ah. Like you know the father like
I don't know like you know like wants to be you know
self-flagellate or something, you know, or you know and he's asking his
son to hit him because he wants to whatever. You see what
I'm saying? Like there could be cases where there's a violent nature
to it and it's with consent, right? But you're right that this
case you could just say it's not even הכאה. haka'ah. Okay, so
let's see what the other answers are. רב דימי בר חיננא אמר
מכה אדם ומכה בהמה. Rav Dimi bar Chinena amar maka adam umaka
behema. מה מכה בהמה לרפואה פטור אף מכה אדם לרפואה פטור. ma
maka behema lirfua patur af maka adam lirfua patur. So that's how
we got onto this, the comparison to בהמה. behema. Now by בהמה
behema we just know it implicitly, right, because if damages... damages is
only when I'm doing something to hurt you. So that's sort of
I think Chanan eventually is getting to. your point. How do we
know by a בהמה behemah that I'm פטור? patur? Right? Now you
could say, well, I'm פטור patur because I made the בהמה behemah
worth more rather than worth less, but as I said, there are
times when I could be trying to do רפואה refuah to the
בהמה behemah and wind up hurting it. Right? So it's not just
that, presumably it's that since it's about damages, that's only when you're
sort of doing something against somebody's will. You know, what you're doing
is considered an act of intrusion or violence, right? So here, you
know, the comparison tells us that also that's how מכה אביו makeh
aviv is understood in that context. Then it goes to the element
of honoring a parent, how would that factor in if a parent
wants you to like hit them, you know, just for like relaxation?
Right. Right, so look, if a- so yes, I mean if a
parent tells you to violate a הלכה, halacha, you don't listen to
them. Okay, but- so whether- so if that were a violation, then
the answer would be yes. Whether it's a violation, right, whether when
it's not just רפואה, refuah, but it's הכאה haka'ah with consent, right?
That's a separate question. Well, suppose if your father did something that's
חייב מיתה, you're- you know, can you be the one to administer?
I think there's actually a case, I think that's actually a תוספתא
Tosefta or a case coming up in the גמרא. Gemara Even if
it's not a violation, if it's going to harm them, can you
not accept their desires, you know, in that instance? That is a
very good question that comes up in contemporary issues about like כיבוד
אב ואם, kibbud av va-em, where a parent asks you to do
something but so you judge it's not in their best interest. Like
it comes up like- right, like a parent asks you to, I
don't know, invest their money in a certain way, or like a
parent says, "no, I'm going to"- like they're clearly not safe to
drive and they're insisting that you let them drive, right? So how
much is it honoring your parents to refuse to let them drive
rather than to allow them to drive, right? We get into whole
questions about autonomy and how- so those are like really good questions.
Driving is injuring somebody else. I understand, driving is injuring somebody else,
right. But anyway, but those are like really good כיבוד אב kibbud
av questions about what their expressed will and what you judge is
in their best interest, but also how the issue of autonomy factors
into best interest, right? Because there could be best interest to help
protect them, but it only does it at the expense of compromising
their autonomy. So those are good questions. Anyway, we're- we're- we're- we're-
we're- we're- we're- we're- we're- we're- we're- we're- we're- we're- we're- we're-
we're- we're- we're- we're- we Maybe if it had been a necessary
byproduct, it would have been considered to be לרפואה. l'refuah. So the
irony being because it was, because it was אינו מתכוון eino miskaven
and it wasn't פסיק רישא psik reisha and it wasn't necessary, therefore
the blood wasn't coming out לרפואה. l'refuah. Okay, still nevertheless, it seems
a little funny. You really mean that any doctor who's doing a
procedure that might accidentally cause some bleeding is over on a שגגת
לאו shiggas lav on an accidental לאו? Okay, still quite funny, but
anyway, but that is interesting, takes it to mean is he taking
this very seriously or not? Well, what if the blood is like
a... like it is פסיק רישא, psik reisha, meaning like you know
it's gonna happen, but it's not the same thing. It's not part
of the רפואה. refuah. It's a necessary byproduct, but it's not what's
actually... right, like the bloodletting, the belief was that the blood coming
out would cause the רפואה. refuah. The surgery, it's like there has
to be blood and you actually try to stop the blood, but
there's no other way to do the surgery without it, right? Okay,
so let's take a look. So גמרא Gemara says one minute, והתנן
מחט של יד ליטול בה את הקוץ. v'ha ditnan machat shel yad
litol bah et hakoatz. So wait a minute, so we talk by
שבת Shabbos that if you take a needle and it's the size,
right, to remove what do you call it, a splinter, that you
can like, you know, that if you can use it like it's
not מוקצה muktzeh whatever because you know you can use it for
going ahead and doing stuff on שבת Shabbos in a way that
you're not doing anything that's אסור on שבת. Shabbos. Okay, so now,
but that makes it sound like that you were... could allow it
because it's like, it sounds like it's a כלי שמלאכתו להיתר kli
shemlachto l'heter that you could, that it's allowed to remove a splinter
on שבת. Shabbos. So the גמרא Gemara says ליחוש שמא יחבל והוי
ליה שגגת סקילה. leichush shema yachbil v'havei lei shiggas skila. How can
you remove a splinter on שבת? Shabbos? Maybe you'll cause some blood
to come out and then you'll be מחלל שבת. m'chaleil Shabbos. Okay,
why not? Also there, they say it's מקלקל. m'kalkeil. So that's what
the גמרא Gemara says: התם מקלקל. hatam m'kalkeil. There it's מקלקל. m'kalkeil.
Okay, so מקלקל m'kalkeil somehow solved your שבת Shabbos problem, but it
didn't solve... but it would... מקלקל m'kalkeil is what? If I'm trying
to take out your splinter on שבת Shabbos and accidentally some blood
comes out, that blood coming out is מקלקל, m'kalkeil, that doesn't help
anybody. But מקלקל m'kalkeil doesn't help you for חובל chovel in your
friend or חובל chovel in a father, because there the whole איסור
issur is that you're מקלקל, m'kalkeil, that you're hurting the person. Okay,
but by שבת, Shabbos, if a blood coming out is מקלקל, m'kalkeil,
that's why it's not a שבת Shabbos violation. So the גמרא Gemara
says הניחא למאן דאמר מקלקל פטור. haniha l'man de'amar m'kalkeil patur. That's
good if מקלקל's m'kalkeil exempt. אלא למאן דאמר מקלקל חייב מאי איכא
למימר? ela l'man de'amar m'kalkeil chayav mai ika l'meimar? But if you
say there's a position that when it comes to wounding, normal things
are constructive, so if you מקלקל m'kalkeil and destructive on שבת, Shabbos,
you're פטור. patur. But wounding by its very nature tends to be
destructive. So there's an opinion that wounding is always חייב on שבת
Shabbos even מקלקל. m'kalkeil. So if that's true, how would you be
allowed to take out a splinter on שבת? Shabbos? If accidentally some
blood came out, even if you're מקלקל, m'kalkeil, you'd be חייב. How
would we allow it? So the גמרא Gemara says no: מאן שמעת
ליה דאמר מקלקל בחבורה חייב רבי שמעון היא. man shemat lei de'amar
m'kalkeil b'chabura chayav Rabbi Shimon hi. That would be רבי שמעון. Rabbi
Shimon. רבי שמעון אומר כל מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה פטור עליה. Rabbi
Shimon amar kol melacha she'eina tzricha legufa patur aleha. You're not trying
to cause the blood to come out. Your intent is to remove
the splinter. So since it's a מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה, melacha she'eina
tzricha legufa, you're going to be פטור. patur. Now again, why didn't
the גמרא Gemara just say you're an אינו מתכוון? eino miskaven? Okay,
מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה melacha she'eina tzricha legufa is a case when
it definitely will happen. So maybe that's the גמרא's Gemara bigger חידוש.
chidush. Although again, the גמרא Gemara could have said, when do we
say you can take out a splinter on שבת? Shabbos? When it
won't definitely cause bleeding. If it will definitely cause bleeding, maybe you're
not allowed. All right, but the גמרא here said even if it
will definitely cause bleeding, it would not be a violation because it
would be מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה. melacha she'eina tzricha legufa. All right,
so we'll review this tomorrow, we sort of rushed through this a
little bit, but the basic point is the גמרא's assuming bizarrely that
even if you're trying to heal your friend, causing some unintentional bleeding
is considered a שגגת לאו. shiggas lav. Whatever happened to אינו מתכוון,
eino miskaven, I have no idea. Whatever happened to the fact that
if it's done for רפואה refuah purposes, it should not be called
smiting I have no idea. The גמרא considers that to be a
שגגת לאו. shiggas lav. Taking out a splinter on שבת Shabbos would
also be an accidental violation if מקלקל m'kalkeil is חייב like רבי
שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Okay, but if מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה melacha she'eina
tzricha legufa is פטור, patur, you're going to be פטור patur on
שבת. Shabbos. But somehow that's enough to get you פטור patur on
שבת, Shabbos, but not enough to solve the case of trying to
take out the splinter from your friend or you know and wounding
your friend in the attempt to try to heal him. Okay, so
we will sort of recap this tomorrow and then we will continue
with this issue about accidental wounding. Yeah.